A Guide to the John Randolph Letters, 1816-1828
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
John Randolph Letters, 1816-1828
The Library of Virginia
22005
54 pages
John Randolph
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Greta Barksdale Brown of Port Deposit, Maryland, 30 January 1942.
Alternative Form Available
23 of the letters also available on microfilm, reel six of the Bruce-Randolph Collection, Misc. Reels 3320-3325 (accession 20232).
Biographical Information
John Randolph of Roanoke was born 2 June 1773 in Prince George County, Virginia, and settled in Charlotte County, Virginia. A member of the prominent Randolph family, he was cousins with Thomas Jefferson and John Marshall. Randolph served in the United States House of Representatives from 1799 to 1813, 1815 to 1817, 1819 to 1825, 1827 to 1829, and 1833, and in the United States Senate from 1825 to 1827. Randolph was an adherent of states' rights and the strict construction of the federal Constitution. He died in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 24 May 1833, freeing his slaves in his will. Randolph was buried at his home in Charlotte County, and later reinterred in Hollywood Cemetery in Richmond, Virginia.
Scope and Content
Letters, 1816-1828, of John Randolph (1773-1833) of Roanoke, Charlotte County, Virginia, to William Jones Barksdale (1794-1859) of Amelia County, Virginia, commenting on politics and personal matters. Three of the letters which were donated have never been located: 1822 February 3, 17, 24. 31 of the 35 letters and 2 of the 3 missing letters are listed in William E. Stokes and Francis L. Berkeley, Jr., The Papers of Randolph of Roanoke.
Contents List
- Letter, 2 March 1816, asking Barksdale to check on a note payable to Randolph from Dr. Banister. Also comments on personal and social matters. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 28 December 1819, asking after mutual friends. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 24 July 1821, commenting on the death of a friend's niece, mentioning his solitude at Roanoke, his plans to travel, and religion. Randolph adds that Robert Garnett informs him that Henry Lee and his wife still reside at Stratford Hall. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 31 July 1821, commenting on the weather and its effects on crops, his workmen, his solitude at Roanoke, and other news. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 7 August 1821, concerning his friends' misfortunes, his horses, the weather, and other news. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 11 December 1821, discussing his trip to Fredericksburg, Virginia. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 15 December 1821, discussing his difficult trip from Fredericksburg to Washington D.C. He comments briefly on politics, mentions with whom he is boarding, and invites Barksdale to visit. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 17 December 1821, thanking Barksdale for his recent letter. Randolph again comments on his travel to Washington, mentions Henry Lee, and gives his best to Barksdale's family. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 27 December 1821, concerning Barksdale's letters, an aborted duel, and a request to hear about friends. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 14 January 1822, concerning news of friends and his own well-being. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 17 January 1822, containing personal and social news. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 3 December 1822, concerning a lapse in his correspondence with Barksdale, Barksdale's father, mutual friends, and Randolph's spirits. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 14 February 1823, containing personal news and news of family and friends. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 18 February 1823, concerning friends. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 10 July 1823, discussing a trip and friends. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 1 August 1823, concerning their correspondence, news of friends, Randolph's reading, and other matters. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 24 October 1823, informing Barksdale of a riding injury, asking after friends, and other news. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 12 January 1824, concerning news of friends and acquaintances. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 10 February 1824, commenting on their correspondence, social news, and the weather. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 24 February 1824, thanking Barksdale for his letter; commenting on his remarks about William Pitt, speeches printed in the newspapers, John Marshall; and discussing social news. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 9 March 1824, sending news of the proceedings in the House of Representatives and commenting on social news. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 16 March 1824, concerning personal news and commenting on the debates in Parliament. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 23 March 1824, discussing personal and social news. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 16 April 1824, discussing the passage of the tariff of 1824, Randolph's mother, Randolph's relationship with Barksdale and Barksdale's family, Henry Lee's book, and other matters. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 7 January 1825, asking why he hasn't heard from Barksdale, and commenting on his trip to Washington. (Folder 2)
- Cover to letter, 10 February 1825. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 15 February 1825, containing personal and social news. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 27 February 1825, concerning a dispute Randolph had in Congress and other matters. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 12 May 1825, concerning the weather and his travel home. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 24 June 1825, concerning letters to Randolph, an invitation from Barksdale, Randolph's health, and other matters. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 29 June 1825, concerning letters from Barksdale and his father. Also a comment on the Richmond Enquirer. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 17 February 1826, discussing social and personal news. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 1 February 1827, discussing the bankruptcy bill in the United States Senate, Barksdale's postponed trip to Washington, and other news. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 28 July 1828, concerning crops, letters, Randolph's half-brother Henry St. George Tucker, weather, Randolph's health and other news. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 21 October 1828, concerning Randolph's health. (Folder 2)